Elias, Hans; Papers ger031
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Hans Elias Papers
1953-1979
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger031
0.5 cubic ft.
Hans Elias, a native of Darmstadt, Germany, was a German-American scientist. This collection contains a number of his contributions to medical research, biology, zoology, and even art in the form of reprints of articles, a photocopy of his manuscript "Abenteuer in Emigration und Wissenschaft," and two reel-to-reel tapes.
Collection X
Biographical Note
Hans Elias was born on June 18, 1907 in Darmstadt, Germany. Elias went to Wekkunstschule Darmstadt where he studied drawing until he enrolled at the Technical University of Darmstadt where he studied mathematics, zoology, and physics. Elias received his doctorate in 1931 and began to teach at various schools in Germany. Prior to the start of World War II, Elias began teaching at the Jewish country Herrlingen and in 1935 he joined his family in Milan, Italy. While in Italy, he began to study cinematography and received a grant from the Swiss aid organization to produce an educational film on the development of amphibious eggs with Ernst Rust, Wilhelm von Mollendorff, and Wolfgang Bargmann.
On April 1, 1939, Elias and his family emigrated to America. Elias was offered a position to teach biology at Middlesex University. During this time, his wife Anneliese Blumenthal, who he had met in Italy, had two children and they became U.S. citizens on November 27, 1944. Elias left the University in 1944 and began working for the Center for Communicable Diseases (CDC) in Atlanta, where he promoted educational medical films. In 1953, Elias was appointed associate professor of anatomy, and in 1960, full professor at the Chicago Medical School. During his time at the Medical School he published a variety of manuscripts and essays.
In 1973, Elias moved back to Germany for a one year research program at Heidelberg University. In 1975, Elias moved back to California and taught at the University of California and City College of San Francisco until his death on April 11, 1985.
Content Description
This collection contains a photocopy of the manuscript "Abenteuer in Emigration und Wissenschaft," by Hans Elias. It also contains reprints of various articles Elias either wrote, co-authored, or otherwise contributed to, as well as two reel-to-reel tapes. All content is based on his work and interests.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged chronologically. There are no series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was transferred to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives prior to July 1981. The donor is unknown.
Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted.
Elias, Hans, 1907-1985; Refugees -- Germany.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees; Manuscripts; Periodicals; Medicine and Health Care
- "Functional Morphology of the Liver," Research in the Service of Medicine, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "The Pregnant Uterus",The Pfizer Series of Anatomical and Pathological Transparencies, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Human Hepatocarcinoma and the Comparative Embryology of the Vertebrate Liver,"Journal of the National Cancer Institute, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "On the Phylogeny of Hair,"American Museum Novitates, 1957 March (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Evolution and the Liver," The Chicago Medical School Quarterly, 1957 May (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Entwicklung und Ausbreitung des primären Leberkarzinoms nebst Bemerkungen über den Einfluß von Metastasen auf die Leber,"Wiener klinische Wochenschrift, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "The Adrenal Cortex In Rheumatoid Arthritis, Rheumatic Fever, and Rheumatic Heart Disease,"The Chicago Medical School Quarterly, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Leber und Gallenwege,"Handbuch der Zoologie: Eine Naturgeschichte Stämme des Tierreiches, 1963 December (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Gründung einer internationalen Gesellschaft für Stereologie," Zeitschrift für wissenschaftliche Mikroskopie und mikroskopische Technik, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Proceedings of the Second International Congress for Stereology, Chicago,"Stereology, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "Stereology of the human renal glomerulus,"Quantitative Methods in Morphology, 1967 April (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Surgical Anatomy of the Liver,"Recent Results in Cancer Research, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Simulacra amatomatica,"Verhandlungen der Anatomischen Gesellschaft, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "Leberzirrhose,"Boehringer Ingelheim, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "Split Brain and the Spread of Carcinoma,"New England Journal of Medicine, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Nuclear Fragmentation in Colon Carcinoma Cells,"Human Pathology, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "Destruction of Leukocytes and Lymph Nodes by Colon Carcinoma—An Observation,"The Cancer Bulletin, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "Embryology, Histology, and the Anatomy of the Biliary System,"The Biliary System, Undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Journalfranz— "Abenteuer in Emigration und Wissenschaft ein Beitrag zur Aufklaerung des Krebsproblems", Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Journalfranz—"The Stereological and other New Approaches to Cancer Research", Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Mew Musical Notation, Hans Elias, Tape 1, Undated (Reel 1)
  General
  9.5 cm/sec 2/2
- Mew Musical Notation, Hans Elias, Tape 2, Undated (Reel 2)